Python is great at managing files, but
sometimes, we need to check to see if a
file exists before running code to either work on
an existing file or create a new one. For example,
knowing if a file exists can determine if we need
to open a file in write mode or append mode, lest
we accidentally overwrite an existing file and
lose valuable information. In a gaming context, if
a player file does not exist, the player may need
to register for a game before playing that game.
This code example, 316-check existence, checks
to see if a file, specifically 316-message.txt,
does not exist and takes action accordingly.
In another domain, we are covering libraries,
but we need one here: the os library, which
is imported on line 1. Libraries add built-in
functions we can run to complete tasks within our
code. One such function is the exists function,
which is part of a path statement and the os
library. This if statement on line 3 checks
whether this 316-message text file exists in the
current path. If the file does not exist, the code
on lines 4 through 8 runs, creating the file,
writing text to the file, and then confirming
that this configuration file is done. On line 9,
we have an else statement, meaning the file does
exist. If that is the case, the code on lines 10
through 13 runs. This code opens, reads, prints,
and closes the file. I will run the code, and
on the first run, we see that the file has been
created. When I run the code a second time, the
file exists, so the contents of the file display.